Solidarity Committee of the Capital District; Records apap042
M.E. Grenander Department of Special Collections & Archives
Solidarity Committee of The Capital District Records
1978-2025
M.E. Grenander Department of Special Collections & Archives
apap042
20.8 cubic ft. and 11 videotapes
The Greyhound Strikers Solidarity Committee of the Capital District was created by Albany-area labor union activists in support of the autumn 1983 Amalgamated Transit Union strike against Greyhound Bus Lines. After the strike, the group was reconstituted as the Solidarity Committee of the Capital District (SCCD) and worked to support hundreds of strikes and labor activities in Eastern New York, across the country, and in Latin America.
Administrative History
The Greyhound Strikers Solidarity Committee of the Capital District was created by Albany, New York-area labor union activists who supported the autumn 1983 Amalgamated Transit Union strike against Greyhound Bus Lines and the organization continued to work for labor and social justice for more than two decades until 2025.
After the 1983 strike ended, the organization was reconstituted as the Solidarity Committee of the Capital District (SCCD), a standing committee of the Albany County Federation of Labor (ACFL) [Solidarity Council of the Capital District (SCCD) meeting minutes, 12 January 1984; Greyhound Lines Strike folder, in Series 3, Subject Files, 1980-90, Solidarity Committee of the Capital District Records, 1980-90. The Greyhound strike precipitated similar developments elsewhere in the United States. See Kim Moody, An Injury to All: The Decline of American Unionism, Haymarket Series, ed. Mike Davis and Michael Sprinker (London: Verso, 1988), 309-13]. The ACFL was the umbrella organization of area AFL-CIO union locals, but the relations between the SCCD, which welcomed members of non-AFL-CIO unions, and the AFL-CIO were often tense. In early 1990, the Schenectady Central Labor Council complained that the SCCD was overstepping the ACFL's geographic jurisdiction. National AFL-CIO officials then asserted that the January 1984 ACFL meeting minutes made no mention of the SCCD's standing committee status and that the SCCD thus had no formal ties to the AFL-CIO [SCCD meeting minutes, 14 May 1987, 11 January 1990, and 24 January 1990, in Series 1, Meeting Minutes, 1983-90, Solidarity Committee of the Capital District Records; Solidarity Notes, February 1990 and April 1990, in Series 2, Solidarity Notes, 1983-90, Solidarity Committee of the Capital District Records, 1984-90]. The SCCD followed through by drafting a resolution that established their ties to the Albany County Federation of Labor since 1984. The resolution was presented at the March 7, 1990 meeting of the ACFL and passed as a constitutional amendment, thereby recognizing the SCCD as a standing committee of the AFL-CIO [Solidarity Committee subject files, Series 3/Box 1/Folder 10. "Albany County Central Federation of Labor- Solidarity Challenge" (1990)].
The SCCD's mission was "to promote solidarity and understanding of the labor movement, through educating and organizing in times of need". Its founders envisioned an organization that would organize and support strikes, protest closures of manufacturing plants, aid unemployed workers, lobby for political and economic reform, and organize non-union workers [SCCD meeting minutes, 12 January 1984]. Their vision continues to guide the SCCD's activities through the present day. They sponsor showings of labor-oriented films, establish training sessions for labor organizers, and consistently support workers engaged in area labor disputes.
While the SCCD's purpose originated with the Amalgamated Transit Union strike in Albany, NY, it was not long before their helping hands extended well beyond New York's Capital Region. Over the years, the SCCD began supporting labor efforts throughout New York State, then across the northeast, until eventually they were active in national issues (ex. the table-grape boycott initiated by the United Farm Workers). Now their specialty is providing financial and psychological support to workers engaged in labor disputes throughout the United States while raising awareness of labor issues worldwide [For the SCCD's support of the grape boycott, see the Grape Boycott -- United Farm Workers folder, in Series 3, Subject Files, 1980-90]. Although chiefly concerned with labor issues, the SCCD is also actively interested in many other social issues. It has ties to reform-oriented organizations such as the Student Association of the University at Albany, SUNY and the New York State [Family] Farm Association [SCCD Meeting Minutes, 14 May 1987, in Series 1, Meeting Minutes, 1983-90, and Solidarity Notes, July 1987, September 1987, June 1988, and April 1990, in Series 2, Solidarity Notes, 1984-90], and has supported campaigns against South African apartheid Solidarity Notes, April 1985 and March 1990, in Series 2, Solidarity Notes, 1984-90, and Apartheid Protests in Albany, NY folder and Divestment Lobbying Day, Albany, NY (March 19, 1985) folder, in Series 3, Subject Files, 1980-90], human-rights abuses in Central and Latin America [SCCD meeting minutes, 9 July 1987 and 17 March 1989, in Series 1, Meeting Minutes, 1983-90, and Solidarity Notes, February 1988, September 1988, February 1990, and March 1990, in Series 2, Solidarity Notes, 1984-90], nuclear weapons proliferation [SCCD meeting minutes, 14 February 1985 and 9 April 1987, in Series 1, Meeting Minutes, 1983-90, and Solidarity Notes, April 1987, in Series 2, Solidarity Notes, 1984-90], and use of synthetic bovine growth hormone [SCCD meeting minutes, 13 April 1989, in Series 1, Meeting Minutes, 1983-90, and Solidarity Notes, August 1987 and March 1990, in Series 2, Solidarity Notes, 1984-90].
In the 1990s, the Solidarity Committee expanded their international efforts to include Latin America, Asia and Africa. Most notably, the Committee was involved in anti-apartheid demonstrations, boycotts, and food and clothing drives. In Latin America, the SCCD was especially interested in the problems going on in Nicaragua and El Salvador. They participated in a caravan to El Salvador that provided much-needed supplies. They also took an active interest in the role of Coca-Cola Corporation in Guatemala and the UFW's grape boycott.
A chairman, a treasurer, and a secretary performed most of the Solidarity Committee's administrative work. Subcommittees charged with coordinating various activities formed as needed. Members attended monthly meetings that were open to all, and yearly dues were contributed voluntarily by unions and individuals alike. Some special events and causes required their own fundraising efforts during the year. The SCCD also published a monthly newsletter until January 2025, Solidarity Notes, which kept activists informed of SCCD's latest concerns. The Committee faithfully maintained its local presence, continuing an annual Martin Luther King, Jr. and Labor Day festivities that it began in Albany years ago. Following the death of longtime leader and Solidarity Notes editor John Funiciello at the end of 2024, the Solidarity Committee opted to dissolve although the members would remain committed to supporting labor and social justice.
Scope and Contents
These records document the formation and activities of the Solidarity Committee of the Capital District (SCCD), a group of activists from New York State's capital district-area labor unions and social-reform organizations, and its links to the larger labor movement.
The collection contains minutes of all SCCD meetings held between November 1983 and May 1990; however, the minutes vary greatly in level of detail. Minutes from 2002-'03 (acquired 2005) are missing months and also vary in their level of detail. Additional administrative materials include correspondence, mailing lists, and financial records. There is also an extensive run (July 1984-February 2009) of the SCCD's monthly newsletter, Solidarity Notes, which began publication in 1984.
The bulk of the collection consists of subject files, some predating the founding of the SCCD and its predecessor organization, the Greyhound Strikers' Solidarity Committee of the Capital District. Most of the files concern labor disputes taking place in northeastern New York, but some files document strikes and other forms of protest taking place elsewhere in the United States or abroad (including Guatemala and South Africa). The files shed light upon the activities of a host of unions, including: Amalgamated Clothing and Textile Workers Union, Amalgamated Transit Union, American Federation of Grain Millers, Aluminum, Brick, and Glass Workers International Union, Brotherhood of Maintenance of Way Employees, Civil Service Employee Association, Communications Workers of America, International Association of Bridge, Structural, and Ornamental Ironworkers, International Association of Machinists, International Federation of Flight Attendants, International Leather Goods, Plastic, and Novelty Workers Union, International Longshoremen's Association, Laundry and Dry Cleaners International Union, National Association of Broadcast Engineers and Technicians, Oil, Chemical, and Atomic Workers Unions, Professional Air Traffic Controllers Organization, Service Employees International Union, United Auto Workers, United Farm Workers, United Food and Commercial Workers, United Mine Workers of America, United Paperworkers International Union, and United Steelworkers of America. Of particular note are copies of personal correspondence between actor and labor activist Ed Asner and SCCD chairman John Funicello.
Many of the files contain photographs, most notably, photos of Cesar Chavez and Jesse Jackson during Chavez's hunger strike in 1988 and photos of Solidarity Committee members at rallies and being arrested.
The subject files in Series 3 are divided into two alphabetical subseries. The materials in those subseries were arranged and described at two different times, several years apart, so rather than try to fit the new acquisitions into the existing subject files (which would have needed extensive rearranging and renumbering), we simply created a second series of subject files, A-Z. With that in mind, a researcher looking for information on the Albany Public Library, for instance, would want to look at both subseries for files on that topic.
Arrangement of the Collection
The collection is organized as follows:
Series 1: Administrative Files, 1983-2000
Series 2: Solidarity Notes, 1984-2025
Series 3: Subject Files, 1978-2000
Series 4: Photographs, 1988-1993
Series 5: Videotapes, 1994-1997, undated
Acquisition Information
In 1990, materials were lent to the University Libraries, M.E. Grenander Department of Special Collections and Archives, for photocopying, which totaled roughly .75 cubic feet. In April 2000, 6 cubic feet of material was transferred, including many of the original files as well as some new material. Additional records were transferred in September 2000, 2001, 2005, annually from 2010-2019, and then again in 2022 and 2024.
Related Materials
Related Collections in the M.E. Grenander Department of Special Collections and Archives can be found in the subject guides for Labor and Conservation and the Environment. Of particular interest are the papers of Lawrence S. Wittner (APAP-100), which provide additional information about social activism in the Capital Region. Additional information about the campaign to stop Hydro-Quebec's James Bay project may be found in the records of Environmental Advocates of New York (APAP-104), the Sierra Club Atlantic Chapter (APAP-130), the North Country James Bay Group (APAP-327), and Nancy Papish (APAP-144).
Existence and Location of Copies
Reproductions of items from this collection are available in the exhibit Documenting Labor Inside and Out: Labor History in New York State's Capital District.
Access
Access to this record group is unrestricted.
Africana Studies; Social Activists and Public Advocates; Schenectady, New York; Labor; Conservation and the Environment; Albany, New York; Labor unions -- Social aspects -- New York (State); Labor unions -- New York (State); Labor unions -- New York (State) -- Schenectady; Solidarity Committee of the Capital District; Greyhound Strikers Solidarity Committee of the Capital District
- Administrative Files, 1983-2000; 1; 0.8 cubic ft.
  Scope and Contents
  This series contains photocopies of meeting agendas and minutes and routine administrative records of the Solidarity Commitee of the Capital District. The minutes document the circumstances leading to the formation of the SCCD, its mission, and many of its subsequent activities. Some sets of minutes are highly detailed, but others consist of brief handwritten notes made on the margins of meeting agendas. Minutes of the SCCD's predecessor organization, the Greyhound Strikers Solidarity Committee of the Capital District, are housed in the Greyhound Lines Strike folder in the Subject Files series.
  Arrangement
  Arranged alphabetically.
  - Agendas, 1984-2005 (Box 1 (1-Administrative Files), Folder 1)
  - Correspondence, 1980-1993 (Box 1 (1-Administrative Files), Folder 2)
  - Correspondence, 1994-2003 (Box 1 (1-Administrative Files), Folder 3)
  - Dues Requests, 1991-2008 (Box 1 (1-Administrative Files), Folder 4)
  - Financial Records, 1984-2001 (Box 1 (1-Administrative Files), Folder 5)
  - Financial Records, Fundraising, 1987 (Box 1 (1-Administrative Files), Folder 6)
  - Flyers and Pamphlets, 1989-2008 (Box 1 (1-Administrative Files), Folder 7)
  - General Information (Mission, by-laws, etc), 1985-1991 (Box 1 (1-Administrative Files), Folder 8)
  - Grant Inquiries, 1993 (Box 2 (1-Administrative Files), Folder 1)
  - Letterhead, ca. 1980s-1990s (Box 2 (1-Administrative Files), Folder 2)
  - Mailing Lists, 1987-1998 (Box 2 (1-Administrative Files), Folder 3)
  - Meeting Minutes, 1983-1993 (Box 2 (1-Administrative Files), Folder 4)
  - Meeting Minutes, 2002-2003 (Box 2 (1-Administrative Files), Folder 5)
  - Membership, 1984-1993 (Box 2 (1-Administrative Files), Folder 6)
  - Membership Meeting, 1992 December (Box 2 (1-Administrative Files), Folder 7)
  - Memorabilia, Undated (Box 2 (1-Administrative Files), Folder 8)
    4 Buttons that say "I'm Labor Party Advocate" in Oversize Box.
  - Notes, Undated (Box 2 (1-Administrative Files), Folder 9)
  - Office Database System Manual, 1996 (Box 2 (1-Administrative Files), Folder 10)
  - Phone Tree, Undated (Box 2 (1-Administrative Files), Folder 11)
  - Programming, 1983-1992 (Box 2 (1-Administrative Files), Folder 12)
  - Programming, Film Series, 1984-1985; 2003-2004 (Box 2 (1-Administrative Files), Folder 13)
  - Solidarity Housing, Inc., 1989-1990 (Box 2 (1-Administrative Files), Folder 14)
- Solidarity Notes, 1984-2025; 2; .8 cubic ft.
  This series consists of the monthly newsletter published by the SCCD. It documents the SCCD's active involvement in a broad array of labor-related issues and the activities of many Capital District and New York State union locals. Missing issues are noted.
  Arranged chronologically.
  - Solidarity Notes, 1984 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    January to June, August, and December 1984 missing.
  - Solidarity Notes, 1985 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    February and August 1985 missing.
  - Solidarity Notes, 1986 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Solidarity Notes, 1987 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    June 1987 missing.
  - Solidarity Notes, 1988 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    May 1988 missing.
  - Solidarity Notes, 1989 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    March 1989 missing.
  - Solidarity Notes, 1990 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Solidarity Notes, 1991 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Solidarity Notes, 1992 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Solidarity Notes, 1993 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Solidarity Notes, 1994 (Box 1, Folder 11)
    October 1994 missing.
  - Solidarity Notes, 1995 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Solidarity Notes, 1996 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Solidarity Notes, 1997 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Solidarity Notes, 1998 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Solidarity Notes, 1999 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Solidarity Notes, 2000 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Solidarity Notes, 2001 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Solidarity Notes, 2002 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Solidarity Notes, 2003 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Solidarity Notes, 2004 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Solidarity Notes, 2005 (Box 2, Folder 3)
    October 2005 missing.
  - Solidarity Notes, 2006 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Solidarity Notes, 2007 (Box 2, Folder 5)
    June-August, October, and November 2007 missing.
  - Solidarity Notes, 2008 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Solidarity Notes, 2009 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Solidarity Notes, 2010 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Solidarity Notes, 2011 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Solidarity Notes, 2012 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Solidarity Notes, 2013 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Solidarity Notes, 2014 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Solidarity Notes, 2015 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Solidarity Notes, 2016 (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Solidarity Notes, 2017 (Box 3, Folder 15)
  - Solidarity Notes, 2018 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Solidarity Notes, 2019 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Solidarity Notes, 2020 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Solidarity Notes, 2021 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Solidarity Notes, 2022 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Solidarity Notes, 2023 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Solidarity Notes, 2024 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Solidarity Notes, 2025 (Box 3, Folder 9)
    Final issue.
- Subject Files, 1978-2000; 3; 13.8 cubic ft.
  This subseries consists of photocopies of newspaper and magazine clippings, legal documents, union publications, and other materials pertaining to issues and campaigns in which the SCCD was interested in and/or involved with. Some files document the SCCD's opposition to apartheid, human-rights abuses, and corporate farming. Others detail its support for labor disputes involving a host of unions including: Amalgamated Clothing and Textile Workers Union, Amalgamated Transit Union, American Federation of Grain Millers, Aluminum, Brick, and Glass Workers International Union, Brotherhood of Maintenance of Way Employees, Civil Service Employee Association, Communications Workers of America, International Association of Bridge, Structural, and Ornamental Ironworkers, International Association of Machinists, International Federation of Flight Attendants, International Leather Goods, Plastic, and Novelty Workers Union, International Longshoremen's Association, Laundry and Dry Cleaners International Union, National Association of Broadcast Engineers and Technicians, Oil, Chemical, and Atomic Workers Unions, Professional Air Traffic Controllers Organization, Service Employees International Union, United Auto Workers, United Farm Workers, United Food and Commercial Workers, United Mine Workers of America, United Paperworkers International Union, and United Steelworkers of America. Of particular note are copies of personal correspondence between actor and labor activist Ed Asner and SCCD chairman John Funicello.
  The material in this subseries was acquired several years after the initial subject files were created. Due to the time-intensive nature of adding them to the existing subject files, then re-numbering the folders and boxes, this second A-Z subseries was added instead. Some of the files found in this subseries contain further information about topics in Subseries #1, including James Bay/HydroQuebec, United Farm Workers, the Workers' Rights Board, General Electric, child labor, and hunger issues. Other files are new to the list, such as Korean labor unions, the National Commission for Democracy in Mexico, Earthwise Education Center, prison reform & correctional officers' rights, Schenectady economic improvements, and many more. As with the first subseries, topics range from local (Albany, NY area & NY State), to national, to international. Some files have just a few pages of information while others have much more, just as some contain accompanying photos while others do not.
  The "Solidarity Committee 25th Anniversary" folder's main content is a DVD showing the SCCD's anniversary celebration on November 1, 2008. The DVD is 2 hours, 36 minutes in length.
  Immediate Source of Acquisition
  Material in this subseries was acquired in and prior to 2000. See Sub-series 2 for alphabetized subject files acquired in 2002 and 2005.
  - AFL/CIO, 1991-1992 (Box 1 (3-Subject Files), Folder 1)
  - AFL/CIO, Assistance Programs especially Drug and Alcohol, 1988-1994 (Box 1 (3-Subject Files), Folder 2)
  - AFL/CIO, "Common Sense Economics for Working Families", 1998 (Box 1 (3-Subject Files), Folder 3)
  - AFL/CIO, Constitution and Bylaws, 1988 (Box 1 (3-Subject Files), Folder 4)
  - AFL/CIO-COPE Convention, New York, 1993; 1998 (Box 1 (3-Subject Files), Folder 5)
  - AFL/CIO, Correspondence, 1989-1998 (Box 1 (3-Subject Files), Folder 6)
  - AFL/CLO, Executive Council Report, 1999 (Box 1 (3-Subject Files), Folder 7)
  - AFL/CLO, Legislative Issues, 1990-1999 (Box 1 (3-Subject Files), Folder 8)
  - AFL/CLO, Miscellaneous, Undated (Box 1 (3-Subject Files), Folder 9)
  - AFL/CLO, Newsletters, 1984-1999 (Box 1 (3-Subject Files), Folder 10)
  - AFL/CIO, Organizing Symposium, 1995 (Box 2 (3-Subject Files), Folder 1)
  - AFL/CLO, Public Employee Division, Mailings, 1997-1999 (Box 2 (3-Subject Files), Folder 2)
  - AFL/CIO, Union Label Service Trades Department, 1998-1999 (Box 2 (3-Subject Files), Folder 3)
  - Airborne Express, Teamsters, 1995 (Box 2 (3-Subject Files), Folder 4)
  - Albany Bus Company Strike, 1991 (Box 2 (3-Subject Files), Folder 5)
  - Albany County Federation of Labor, Minutes and Notes, 1998-2000 (Box 2 (3-Subject Files), Folder 6)
  - Albany Public Library, 1995 (Box 2 (3-Subject Files), Folder 7)
  - Albany Yellow Communications, Inc., 1991; 1997 (Box 2 (3-Subject Files), Folder 8)
  - Alcoa Strike, Massena, NY, Aluminum, Brick, and Glass Workers International Union, Local 420, 1986 (Box 2 (3-Subject Files), Folder 9)
  - Alliance for Democracy, 1997 (Box 2 (3-Subject Files), Folder 10)
  - Allied Industrial Workers, Local 837, 1993 (Box 2 (3-Subject Files), Folder 11)
  - AlTech Specialty Steel, Strike, 1986; 1997 (Box 2 (3-Subject Files), Folder 12)
  - Aluminum Workers, 1993-1994 (Box 3 (3-Subject Files), Folder 1)
  - American Income Life Insurance, Labor Letter, 1989-1999 (Box 3 (3-Subject Files), Folder 2)
  - American Linen Supply Company Strike, Laundry and Dry Cleaners International Union, Local 201, 1985 (Box 3 (3-Subject Files), Folder 3)
  - American Postal Workers Union, Arbitration Awards, 1983-1989 (Box 3 (3-Subject Files), Folder 4)
  - American Postal Workers Union, Clippings, 1989-1999 (Box 3 (3-Subject Files), Folder 5)
  - American Postal Workers Union, Committee on Political Actions, 1989 (Box 3 (3-Subject Files), Folder 6)
  - American Postal Workers Union, Compliance with the 1988 Budget, GAO Report (Box 3 (3-Subject Files), Folder 7)
  - American Postal Workers Union, Conferences, 1998-2000 (Box 3 (3-Subject Files), Folder 8)
  - American Postal Workers Union, Correspondence, 1987-1999 (Box 3 (3-Subject Files), Folder 9)
  - American Postal Workers Union, A Guide for the Craft Employee in Dealing with the US Postal Inspection Service, 1988 (Box 3 (3-Subject Files), Folder 10)
  - American Postal Workers Union, Housekeeping Postal Office Maintenance Grievance, Undated (Box 3 (3-Subject Files), Folder 11)
  - American Postal Workers Union, Local Safety Officer's Handbook, 1992 (Box 4 (3-Subject Files), Folder 1)
  - American Postal Workers Union, Miscellaneous, Undated (Box 4 (3-Subject Files), Folder 2)
  - American Postal Workers Union, Newsletters, 1989; 1999 (Box 4 (3-Subject Files), Folder 3)
  - American Postal Workers Union, Pregnancy Leave, 1978-1985 (Box 4 (3-Subject Files), Folder 4)
  - American Postal Workers Union, Tentative Collective Bargaining Agreement, 1998-2000 (Box 4 (3-Subject Files), Folder 5)
  - American Postal Workers Union, USPS Albany Division Drivers Manual, Undated (Box 4 (3-Subject Files), Folder 6)